This is the Bop.
هذه هي (البوب).
The Bop is a type of social dance.
(البوب) هي نوع من الرقصات الشعبية
Dance is a language,
الرقص هو لغة،
and social dance is an expression that emerges from a community.
الرقص الشعبي هو نوع من التعابير التي تنتج عن مجتمع ما.
A social dance isn't choreographed by any one person.
الرقصة الشعبية لا يمكن أن تُفشل من قبل شخص واحد
It can't be traced to any one moment.
و لا يمكن تعقبها للحظة زمنية واحدة.
Each dance has steps that everyone can agree on,
لكل رقصة حركات معينة، و التي يتفق عليها الجميع
but it's about the individual and their creative identity.
و لكن يتدخل فيها الأفراد و هوياتهم الإبداعية.
Because of that,
و بسبب ذلك،
social dances bubble up,
الرقصات الشعبية تستمر بالتصاعد،
they change
و التغير
and they spread like wildfire.
و تنتشر كالنار في الهشيم.
They are as old as our remembered history.
إنهم قدماء بقدم تاريخنا المعروف.
In African-American social dances,
في الرقصات الأفرو-أميركية الشعبية،
we see over 200 years
يمكننا أن نشاهد 200 عام
of how African and African-American traditions influenced our history.
من تأثير عادات الأفارقة و الأفرو-أميركيين على تاريخنا.
The present always contains the past.
الحاضر يحتوي الماضي دوماً.
And the past shapes who we are
و الماضي يحدد ماهيتنا
and who we will be.
و من سنكون.
(Clapping)
(تصفيق)
The Juba dance was born from enslaved Africans' experience
لقد وُلدت رقصة ال(جوبا) من تجربة العبودية الإفريقية
on the plantation.
في المزارع.
Brought to the Americas,
و من ثم جُلبت الى الأميركيتين،
stripped of a common spoken language,
مرتبطة بلغة محكية منتشرة،
this dance was a way for enslaved Africans to remember where they're from.
كانت هذه الرقصة بمثابة تذكير للأفارقة المُستعبدين بأصولهم.
It may have looked something like this.
ربما بدت شبيهة بهذه.
Slapping thighs,
تصفيق بالفخذين،
shuffling feet
حركة أرجل عشوائية
and patting hands:
و تربيت بالأيدي:
this was how they got around the slave owners' ban on drumming,
كانت هذه طريقتهم في التفاف على على قانون منع الطبول من قبل الأسياد
improvising complex rhythms
ليرتجلوا إيقاعات معقدة
just like ancestors did with drums in Haiti
كما فعل الأسلاف بالطبول في (هاييتي)
or in the Yoruba communities of West Africa.
أو في المستعمرات الأوروبية في غرب أفريقيا.
It was about keeping cultural traditions alive
كان الأمر يتمحور حول بقاء التقاليد الثقافية على قيد الحياة
and retaining a sense of inner freedom
و المحافظة على إحساس داخلي بالحرية
under captivity.
تحت الأسر.
It was the same subversive spirit that created this dance:
و كانت نفس تلك الروح التي أدت الى نشأة هذه الرقصة
the Cakewalk,
ال(كيك ووك)
a dance that parodied the mannerisms of Southern high society --
و هي رقصة تسخر من سلوكيات نخبة المجتمع من جنوب البلاد
a way for the enslaved to throw shade at the masters.
أي أنها وسيلة للعبيد ليتناسوا وجود الأسياد.
The crazy thing about this dance
الجنون الحقيقي بخصوص هذه الرقصة
is that the Cakewalk was performed for the masters,
هو أنه ال(كيك ووك) كانت تُؤدى أمام الأسياد و لأجلهم،
who never suspected they were being made fun of.
و الذين لم يلاحظوا أبدا بأن الراقصين يسخرون منهم.
Now you might recognize this one.
الآن، قد تتمكنوا من معرفة هذه.
1920s --
(عشرينات القرن العشرين)
the Charleston.
ال(الشارلستون).
The Charleston was all about improvisation and musicality,
تتمحور ال(الشارلستون) حول الارتجال مع الموسيقا،
making its way into Lindy Hop,
لتشق طريقها الى أشكال أخرى كال(لاندي هوب)،
swing dancing
رقصة ال(سوينغ)
and even the Kid n Play,
أو حتى ال(الكيد ان بلي)،
originally called the Funky Charleston.
و بالأساس كانت تسمى (فانكي شارلستون).
Started by a tight-knit Black community near Charleston, South Carolina,
لتبدأ هذه الرقصة من مجتمع الزنوج المتماسك قرب مدينة شارلستون في كارلينا الجنوبية،
the Charleston permeated dance halls
و من ثمّ تغلغلت إلى دور الرقص
where young women suddenly had the freedom to kick their heels
عندما أصبح للنساء مطلق الحرية بالطقطقة بكعوبهم
and move their legs.
و تحريك أقدامهم.
Now, social dance is about community and connection;
و الآن، الرقص الشعبي يتمحور حول المجتمع والتواصل
if you knew the steps,
إذا كنت تعرف الحركات،
it meant you belonged to a group.
هذا يعني أنك تنتمي للمجموعة.
But what if it becomes a worldwide craze?
و لكن ماذا إذا أصبح جنوناً عالمياً؟
Enter the Twist.
نأتي الآن إلى رقصة ال(تويست).
It's no surprise that the Twist can be traced back to the 19th century,
إنه ليس من المفاجئ أنه بإمكاننا الرجوع بتاريخ هذه الرقصة الى القرن التاسع عشر،
brought to America from the Congo
آتية إلى أميركا من الكونغو
during slavery.
خلال عهد العبودية.
But in the late '50s,
و لكن في أواخر الخمسينات،
right before the Civil Rights Movement,
مباشرة قبل حراك الحقوق المدنية،
the Twist is popularized by Chubby Checker and Dick Clark.
انتشرت ال(تويست) عن طريق (تشوبي تشيكير) و (ديك كلارك).
Suddenly, everybody's doing the Twist:
و فجأة، أصبح الجميع يرقصون ال(تويست):
white teenagers,
من مراهقين بيض،
kids in Latin America,
إلى أطفال في أميركا اللاتينية،
making its way into songs and movies.
لتدخل بعدها في الأغاني و السينما.
Through social dance,
عن طريق الرقص الشعبي،
the boundaries between groups become blurred.
تتلاشى الحدود بين الجماعات البشرية.
The story continues in the 1980s and '90s.
تُستكمل القصة في الثمانينيات و التسعينات.
Along with the emergence of hip-hop,
جنبا إلى جنب مع ظهور موسيقى الـ(هيب هوب)،
African-American social dance took on even more visibility,
رقصة شعبية أفرو-أمريكية أخذت تبدو أكثر وضوحا،
borrowing from its long past,
مستعيرةً من الماضي الطويل،
shaping culture and being shaped by it.
لتغير من الثقافة و تتغير بها.
Today, these dances continue to evolve, grow and spread.
اليوم، هذه الرقصات تستمر بالتطور و النمو، والانتشار
Why do we dance?
لماذا نرقص؟
To move,
لنتحرك،
to let loose,
لنطلق العنان لأنفسنا،
to express.
لنعبّر.
Why do we dance together?
لماذا نرقص معاً؟
To heal,
للشفاء،
to remember,
للتذكر،
to say: "We speak a common language.
و لنقول:"نحن نتحدث لغة واحدة.
We exist
نحن موجودون
and we are free."
و نحن أحرار."